You can talk to me, we can laugh and smile.
A Kiowa time trial.
Let's get started with Day 13 for the month of September.
Hi, everyone. I'm Steve Ceresi.
And I'm Jenny Skidmore. Thanks for joining us.
It's our last SPR training this month, and we have something special.
We'll talk about kimonos.
You might wear a kimono, or with so many tourists coming to Japan and renting kimonos,
you might have a conversation about a kimono.
Soko de kimono wo mite, oh, beautiful kimono dake de waru no de wa nakute,
niyau to ka, ariba kimono ni tsuite kikareta toki ni kotaeru benrina hyougen mo awasete minitsukimashou.
And once again, today's lesson will be in almost all English.
今回もほぼオーディングして頑張りましょう。
OK, let's begin with our first time trial.
S-P-R Training
I'll say something in Japanese,
and you express it in English within the time limit.
Here's the first one.
その着物はあなたにすごく似合っていますね。
Start with,
That kimono looks...
Go ahead.
Good. Here's the next one.
Nihonde kaimashita ka?
Dokode kaimashita ka?
Sono tabi wa dokode kaimashita ka?
For tabi, just use tabi socks. Go ahead.
Start with, but I haven't.
Go ahead.
お正月には必ず着物を着ます。
Start with, I always wear...
Go ahead.
母は割とよく着物を着ます。
この着物について教えますね。
これは京都で作られました。
母がくれました。
OK, time's up.
How did you do?
Did you try to say each one?
Now, Jenny and I will show you the sample answers and give you some advice.
So listen closely.
その着物はあなたにすごく似合っていますね。
That kimono looks great on you.
すごく似合ってます is 〜 looks great on you.
Imagine Jenny is wearing a kimono, and let's say it to her.
Jenny, that kimono looks great on you.
いってみよう。
Well, thanks.
Here's the next one.
日本で買いましたか?
Did you get it in Japan?
どこで買いましたか?
Where did you get it?
そのタビはどこで買いましたか?
Where did you get those tabi socks?
There's no direct translation for tabi in English.
So, I suggest tabi socks.
Some people say toe socks.
But when we're talking about kimono, we might as well introduce the word tabi this way.
Where did you get those tabi socks?
Okay, here's the next one.
よく着物を着ますか?
Do you wear a kimono often?
クローゼットに着物があります。
I have a kimono in my closet.
でもずっと着ていません。
But I haven't worn it for a long time.
ずっと着ていません。
I haven't wearの過去分詞worn.
I haven't worn it そしてずっとfor a long time.
Let's say it after Jenny.
But I haven't worn it for a long time.
お正月には必ず着物を着ます。
I always wear a kimono for New Year's.
母は割とよく着物を着ます。
My mom wears a kimono pretty often.
この着物について教えますね。
I'll tell you about this kimono.
これは京都で作られました。
母がくれました。
This was made in Kyoto. My mom gave it to me.
Okay. Did you understand today's phrases?
All right. Now it's your turn to try them one more time.
This is your chance to do a little better than before.
Jenny will say the answers after the pause.
So do your best. Okay, let's go.
その着物はあなたにすごく似合っていますね。
That kimono looks great on you.
日本で買いましたか?
Did you get it in Japan?
どこで買いましたか?
Where did you get it?
Sono tabi wa doko de kaemashita ka?
Where did you get those tabi socks?
Yoku kimono wo kimasu ka?
Do you wear a kimono often?
Kruzetto ni kimono ga arimasu.
I have a kimono in my closet.
でもずっと着ていません。
But I haven't worn it for a long time.
お正月には必ず着物を着ます。
I always wear a kimono for New Year's.
母は割とよく着物を着ます。
この着物について教えますね。
これは京都で作られました。
母がくれました。
This was made in Kyoto. My mom gave it to me.
Okay, time's up.
Well, how was your second try?
Jenny-san, kimono mochi desu ka ne?
Jenny, do you have a kimono?
Well, I don't have a kimono, but I have worn a kimono before.
Was it for a special occasion?
Well, I wore it in Kyoto for a TV show.
Oh, really?
Someone helped me wear the kimono,
and I was so impressed.
There are so many steps to wearing a kimono.
Well, that's a precious experience.
So many people come to Japan,
and one thing they want to do is wear a kimono.
And it's a great chance to have a conversation with them.
Get on board.
And let's practice speaking together.
See you next time on...
Ikaewa Time Trial
Bye-bye